<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abba father: or, a plaine and short direction concerning priuate prayer Also, sundry godly admonitions concerning time, and the well vsing of it. By Elnathan Parr, minister of the word.</title>
            <author>Parr, Elnathan, d. 1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836208</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1526:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abba father: or, a plaine and short direction concerning priuate prayer Also, sundry godly admonitions concerning time, and the well vsing of it. By Elnathan Parr, minister of the word.</title>
                  <author>Parr, Elnathan, d. 1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by F. K[ingston] for Samuel Man, and are to be sold at the signe of the Swan, in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F¹² [-A1] G² [-G2].</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:465:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:465:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ABBA FATHER: <hi>OR,</hi> A PLAINE AND ſhort direction concerning <hi>Priuate Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, SVNDRY GODLY AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions concerning Time, and the well vſing of it.</p>
            <p>By ELNATHAN PARR, Miniſter of the <hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 8.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye haue receiued the ſpirit of Adoption, whereby we cry, <hi>Abba Father.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 5.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Redeeme the time becauſe the dayes are euill.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Man,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Swan, in Pauls Church-yard. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:465:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:465:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY HONORABLE and moſt worthy Lady, the Lady <hi>Iane Cornwaleys,</hi> wife to the very Noble and <hi>Religious Gentleman,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter NATHANAEL BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CON, <hi>Eſquire, Grace and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raier is the true Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per element, without which hee can no more liue, then without fire: Breath is the inſtrument of the life of the body; Prayer is the breath of the
<pb facs="tcp:465:3"/>ſoule: I haue obſerued in many a difficulty of this breathing, which I haue endeauoured ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my ſimple skill, ſomething to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie by this directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I humbly deſire your Ladiſhip to giue it leaue to paſſe vnder your worthy Name: I confeſſe it can bee no waies vſeful to you; but it may bee to weaker Chriſtians, who are yet as babes newly begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to cry, <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein I preſent my thankfull mind to your
<pb facs="tcp:465:3"/>Ladiſhip, whoſe great fauours and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, my deſerts can neuer equall. I daily pray for your Ladiſhip, that as God hath highly aduanced your Name on earth for godlineſſe, ſo he would in the time appointed, glorifie your ſoule in heauen, for the merits of your Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted ſeruant in all humble obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, <hi>ELN. PARR.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:465:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:465:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER, encreaſe of all good gifts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O condemne a ſet forme of prayer, argues want of ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and wiſdome. In pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayers in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation it is neceſſary to haue a preſcribed forme called Liturgy, or Diuine Seruice, which for more eaſe of memory is to be read out of the booke. The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt Fathers (in the peace
<pb facs="tcp:465:5"/>of the Church) haue by their practice ſo iudged it: many Councels haue appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, and the beſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches follow it.</p>
            <p>As for priuate prayer of one Chriſtian alone, it is more expedient that it bee vttered without a booke; and the moſt compleat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that duty is, when a Chriſtian is able not onely to repeate and apply to his owne ſoule and conſcience a prayer concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by another, but alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fit matter, and heads ſuteable to the occaſion, to conceiue and vtter prayers of his own. Yet ſeeing there are many to whom God
<pb facs="tcp:465:5"/>hath not giuen memory and vnderſtanding fitting, to expreſſe in a continued ſpeech the deſires of their hearts; for ſuch haue I written this direction.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why I haue vndertaken this buſineſſe, conſidering there are ſo many good Prayer-bookes in euery mans hand, is, firſt, becauſe, though it bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable to vſe a booke, yet it is more comfortable to pray of our ſelues, whoſe wants may be ſuch, as that we ſhall hardly finde them ſufficiently expreſſed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny booke: for euery man is beſt acquainted with his owne heart.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:465:6"/>
Secondly, a man may be caſt into priſon, and his booke taken from him: how vncomfortably muſt he needs paſſe his time, if he cannot pray without his booke. The booke cannot be vſed in the darke, when we may haue iuſt occaſion to pray. The booke may bee forgotten, or loſt: but if thou attaineſt this gift, thou canſt neuer looſe it, vnleſſe thou looſeſt thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For theſe reaſons I commend this Treatiſe to thee, which I could haue amplified further, and it may be, clothed it with a more elegant ſtile. But I
<pb facs="tcp:465:6"/>aimed at thy profit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that I directed beginners, for whom ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and plainneſſe are moſt fitting.</p>
            <p>If thou profiteſt by this which I heere propound to thee; praiſe God: and in thy prayers forget not him, who hath at leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured to further thee. If thou profiteſt not; yet I haue done my good will, for the which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee to loue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy true friend in Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Eln. Parr.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="directions">
            <pb facs="tcp:465:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:465:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Abba Father.</hi> OR A PLAINE AND ſhort direction <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning priuate Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rayer is a holy conference of a godly mind with God, whereby belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, we aske things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and giue thanks for benefits receiued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:465:8"/>
Prayer is either
<list>
                  <item>Mentall onely, or</item>
                  <item>Vocall alſo, this
<list>
                        <item>1. Extraordinary, or</item>
                        <item>2. Ordinary, this
<list>
                              <item>1. Publike, or</item>
                              <item>2. Priuate, this
<list>
                                    <item>1. Leſſe priuate with the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</item>
                                    <item>2. More priuate, by one alone.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Publike is that which is vſed in the publicke Congregation, by the Miniſter with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Priuate is that which is vſed by priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in priuate places; of this is this preſent Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>It is a great bleſſing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:465:8"/>that God will vouchſafe to attend and receiue our deuotions poured forth in any priuate place.</p>
            <p>Great Perſonages re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire places ſutable to their Greatnes: but thy great God reſpects not the place, how meane ſo euer, but the neceſſitie of his ſeruant.</p>
            <p>Where there is a <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy,</hi> a <hi>Daniel,</hi> or a <hi>Ionas;</hi> a dungeon, a Lions den, the belly of a Whale are godly Oratories.</p>
            <p>But remember, that neuer any man prayed well priuately, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned or neglected the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:465:9"/>publicke prayers in the Church.</p>
            <p>For the comfortable performance of this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſeruice, two things are to be conſidered:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Preparation.</item>
                  <item>2. Execution.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Preparation is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſiderate fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelues for this dutie.</p>
            <p>This is neceſſary in a threefold reſpect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of the perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom wee preſent our ſelues, which is the Almighty.</item>
               <item>2 Of the importance of the thing it ſelfe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:465:9"/>which is a ſpeciall part of diuine worſhip.</item>
               <item>3 Of the conſequence of this duty, which is the obtaining of things needfull, for this and a better life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Vnto this preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeuen things belong.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, a fit place, which muſt bepriuat<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma.</hi> 6.5.6.</note>: Chriſt himſelfe went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mountaine alone to pray<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma.</hi> 14.23.</note>: and into a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary place<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.35.</note>. So <hi>Peter</hi> went vp to the vpper part of the houſe<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.9.</note>: not but that it is lawfull to pray euery where<note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8.</note>. But priuacy is to be choſen, that being ſequeſtred
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:465:10"/>from company, we may the more fully deſcend into our owne hearts, and be the freer from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and from diſcurſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and wandring of mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, a fit time. All times are for this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</note>; euen the night is a ſweet time for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as <hi>Dauids</hi> midnights practiſe<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.62.</note>, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours whole nights ſpent in prayer<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.19.</note> doe teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Thou canſt not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, but at certaine ſet times ſpeake to great men: but thou maiſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:465:10"/>ſpeak to thy God.</p>
            <p>Yet for ſet and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary prayer, ſome choiſe of time would be vſed: I think it to be moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to begin and end the day with praier; as the ordinary ſacrifice of the Iewes, was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, a freedom of mind from thoughts of the world, and the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires thereof: for earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things are heauy, and their thoughts depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which hinder the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the mind to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Repentance and a holy purpoſe of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:465:11"/>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6. <hi>and</hi> 66.18. <hi>Eſay</hi> 15.1. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3 22.</note>. They muſt needs diſtruſt to receiue that which they deſire, who purpoſe not to doe that which God requires. The cry of our vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted-for ſinnes, is louder then the crie of our voyce. As in a wound a plaiſter preuailes not, while the iron remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth within; ſo neither praier, while ſinne rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth within.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, Reading; I would aduiſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prayer, there might be reading of a Chapter in the Bible, or a Pſalm, if buſineſſe permit, both for the increaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:465:11"/>and for the better calling home of the mind to the buſineſſe in hand.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Sixthly, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Prayers called Eiaculations, which are ſudden liftings vp of the heart to God, vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold occaſions occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euery day, come not within this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: but ſet prayer requires ſometime to be ſpecially imployed this way. As the Muſitian firſt tunes his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before he play vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: ſo both the mind would be put in frame, and the matter fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:465:12"/>when we peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God.</p>
            <p>Doe no temporall buſineſſe raſhly: more eſpecially when thou ſpeakeſt to God, bee not raſh with thy mouth,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1.</note> leſt thou take Gods name in vaine; which many times comes to paſſe by vaine repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by words, idle, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, and: without ſenſe; when we dare ſo ſuddenly enter into this action.</p>
            <p>Meditation therfore is neceſſary, which muſt be fiue fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Of the Maieſty of God no moue reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:465:12"/>As mortall men endure not the ſawcie and vnreſpectfull carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of ſuiters: ſo GOD much more requires, that wee ſhould ſerue him in feare<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11.</note>, as <hi>Dauid</hi> in feare will worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Of his mercy, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and truth, to breede confidence; for hee that doubteth, receiueth not<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.7.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Of the excellencie of the benefits we deſire, to make vs willing; which are the fauour of God, forgiueneſſe of ſin, ſanctification, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:465:13"/>life.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Of our own neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and wants to make vs feruent: for as tart ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſharpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtomack; ſo the due pondering and ſenſe of our wants, whets off the dull blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our affections, and ſets an edge on them to prayer.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Of the words and whole frame of our ſpeech, that we may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a reaſonable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and pray with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.14.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Seuenthly, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous faſting is a notable helpe to prayer, and is often commended to vs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:465:13"/>in the Word; which is either publike or priuat.</p>
            <p>Priuate is a voluntary abſtaining from dinner or ſupper, or both, as our bodies will beare, and from all delicacies for one day or moe, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to make vs the more fit for prayer, and the ſeuere practice of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>But this is a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and helpe for extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, not for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary prayer.</p>
            <p>When there is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this, remember three things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:465:14"/>
               <item>1. The time of the vſe of it.</item>
               <item>2. The ends of the vſe of it.</item>
               <item>3. The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the vſe of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 The time is, firſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſome great cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; ſecondly, or of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary repentance for ſome ſpeciall ſinne; thirdly, or when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to obtain ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ends in faſting are two:</p>
            <p>Firſt, a fitting our ſelues to prayer, that we may be the more liuely and earneſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:465:14"/>bee a helpe and a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our ſorrow for ſinne, and of our humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation before God<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The conditions are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That it bee not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, for in it ſelfe it is no part of GODS worſhip. The Kingdom of heauen is not in meat and drinke<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That it be not with the opinion of merit; for whether we eate or eate not, we are neither the more nor the leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God<note n="r" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That wee faſt from ſinne, otherwiſe our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is Phariſaicall,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:465:15"/>not regarded<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa</hi> 58.5.6 <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.12.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thus much of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, now of the other part, which is executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>In the execution or performance of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of prayer, I conſider two things,
<list>
                  <item>1. The matter,</item>
                  <item>2. The forme.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The matter of our prayers muſt bee onely that which is according to Gods reuealed will<note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 15 14.</note>, the ſumme whereof is compriſed in that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine forme, left vnto the Church by our Sauiour Chriſt, called the Lords Prayer, and may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:465:15"/>to three heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with the remouing of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries.</item>
               <item>2. Our owne ſaluation, with the remouing of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries.</item>
               <item>3. The vſe of this life. with the remouing of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The forme is either
<list>
                  <item>1. Inward or</item>
                  <item>2. outward.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to the inward, ſixe things are requiſite.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Sinceritie of our deſires, that we pray not for faſhion like hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, but with honeſt hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Feruency. Such
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:465:16"/>prayers obtaine<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5.16.</note>, which he is not worthie to doe, which askes in that manner, as he cares not to receiue. GOD loues an importunate begger. Prayers are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe which muſt be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with fire.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Faith, whereby we certainely beleeue and expect the performance of our requeſts. God is prouoked when we beg that which we looke not to receiue: our faith is grounded;</p>
            <p n="1">1 On the promiſe, truth and power of him who hath promiſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 On the fatherly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:465:16"/>of God; for if he bee our Father, hee will much more then our earthly fathers giue vs good things<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.13.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3 On the merit of Chriſt, which is infinite.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Patience, whereby we willingly ſubmit our ſelues to Gods wil, both in regard of the things we aske, and of the time and meanes of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
            <p>Things that directlie concerne Gods glory, and are neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation we muſt expect abſolutely: but things tranſitorie, with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition (if God ſee them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:465:17"/>to be good for vs). Better knowes the Phyſition what is good for the ſicke, then the Patient: yea many times he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs exceedingly, in not doing our will, but his owne.</p>
            <p>Wiſh not that to bee granted which thou wilt; but labour thou to will that, which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to grant.</p>
            <p>It is leſſe grieuous not to obtaine that which thou wilt, then to will that which is not fit for thee to obtaine.</p>
            <p>For the time; we muſt not preſcribe vnto God, but waite vpon him.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:465:17"/>
5 Perſeuerance: God ſometime deferres the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of our requeſts; not that he deſpiſeth vs, but for our exerciſe, that we may be the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt till, and the more thankfull when we haue receiued. Things deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought are dearely eſteemed.</p>
            <p>Somtime God grants vs not that we aske, but that which is better, as in the example of <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.89.</note>.</p>
            <p>Grace to ſtand in temptation, is better then deliuerance. And faith is a ſurer rule of our exauditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Charity: to pray
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:465:18"/>for others as well as for our ſelues: for the King and Queenes moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſties, and for their children, and for all men<note n="y" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2.</note>, for our very enemies and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44.</note>, as did our bleſſed Sauiour<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34.</note>, and the Proto-martyr Saint <hi>Stephen</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60.</note>: for wicked men, as <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>Sodom</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.</note>. If he for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> where was but one <hi>Lot,</hi> much more we for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> wherein are ſo many the ſonnes and daughters of God.</p>
            <p>He that is not with men in the charitie of Brethren, ſhall not bee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:465:18"/>with God in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſonnes. Theſe onely can cry <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and are heard.</p>
            <p>The whole Church prayeth for thee, pray thou for it.</p>
            <p n="2">The outward form is in two things,
<list>
                  <item>1 Compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and</item>
                  <item>2 Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is either
<list>
                  <item>1 Of the geſture of the body. or</item>
                  <item>2 Of words, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the meaning of our mind.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 For the firſt: A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers geſture is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, not preſcribed in the word: The Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can ſtood<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.25.</note>: <hi>Eliah</hi> ſate<note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.4.</note>: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> lay<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 38.2.</note>: <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> kneeled<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.40. <hi>and</hi> 20.36.</note>:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:465:19"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> fell on their faces<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 16.22.</note>: <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſtretched out his hands<note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.22</note>: our Sauiour lift vp his eyes<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.41.</note>: the Publican caſt them downe, and alſo ſmote his breaſt<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13.</note>: <hi>Dauid</hi> and Chriſt wept<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.67. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</note>.</p>
            <p>Of all theſe diuers ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, I commend for ordinary, theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1 A comely and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent kneeling, which is a ſigne and helpe of our humiliation. The rude and vnmannerly leaning, lying along, and ſitting of many, eſpecially at publike prayers, is worthy to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:465:19"/>cenſured, and argues an irreligious heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A lifting vp of the hands and eyes; a ſigne and a helpe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence and feruency.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Sometime a caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe of the eyes, and ſmiting the breaſt; to ſignifie and help our deiection, and ſhame for our ſinnes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Teares alſo &amp; grones would exceedingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our prayers and praiſes, more then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels and Pearles our bodies: Teares are trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured vp in the Lords bottel<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8.</note>; and are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:465:20"/>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12.</note>.</p>
            <p>As theſe, and the like geſtures iſſue from the feruent deſire of the heart: ſo they reflect vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible affections, by theſe viſible actions are the more inflamed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is of words; it muſt be remembred, that words are not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply neceſſary to priuate prayer: as appeares in the example of <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15.</note> and <hi>Anna</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13.</note>. For praier is not a lip-, but a hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labour; and God heares the heart<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27.</note>. But it is very conuenient to vſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:465:20"/>words.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe the tongue was created principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this vſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe ſpeech moues the ſenſes, being to the deuotion of the mind, as bellowes are to the fire.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe it keepes the thoughts from wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring.</p>
            <p>In framing the ſpeech, words may not bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; but plaine, apt, and ſignificant: Fine words, and eloquent phraſes are not that wherein God delights; but reuerence, contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, faith, and the gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:465:21"/>of the ſpirit, how homely ſoeuer the words be.</p>
            <p>Striue more to pray with feeling, then to bee eloquent. Wee vſe elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to perſwade men; wee pray not to perſwade God; but</p>
            <p n="1">1 To ſhew our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, becauſe he hath commanded this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To teſtifie our faith; that wee depend on him, and expect from him all good things.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That wee may be fit to receiue according to our need.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:465:21"/>
Prayer is a golden chaine, which God lets downe from heauen; when we lay hold of it, we thinke we draw God to vs; but indeed, wee are by it drawne vp to him.</p>
            <p>Eloquent praying is lawfull, if it be not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: but verbal praiers are exceeding dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Diſpoſition is of the matter of our prayer:</p>
            <p>In which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<list>
                  <item>1 An orderly placing of the parts.</item>
                  <item>2 An inlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:465:22"/>
1 Order is bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and very neceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leſt wee vſe idle repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bee confuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things to bee auold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> when wee ſpeake beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> wiſe men, much m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> when wee ſpeake to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> infinite God. Forwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of obſeruing Order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> goe forward and ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ward, after an vncom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner, vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly repeating ouer the ſame things; faring like hounds at a loſſe; and hauing vnaduiſedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſpeake, know not how wiſely to make an end.</p>
            <p>This kind of praying
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:465:22"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſome degree comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der the cenſure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abling.</p>
            <p>Some thinke that we muſt neuer pray, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the ſudden &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raordinary inſtinct and potion of the Spirit. This is a fancie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe which practice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his, cannot auoid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>conueniences named. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides, the multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of our wants; the ſlipperineſſe of our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie; the ſlowneſſe of our conceit; the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; the wandring of our thoughts, and the imperfection of our vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:465:23"/>require ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-thoughts of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which we are to ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all which weakneſſes are by meditation and order much relieued.</p>
            <p>God is the God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and likes not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence or vnaduiſednes in his ſeruice. Doe thou ſtudie to ſerue him.</p>
            <p>As the wiſe Preacher ſpeakes not at all ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatſoeuer comes on his tongues end, but prepares in his minde the generall parts and heads of his exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo doe thou in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, loſt thou offer the ſacrifice of fooles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:465:23"/>
As the Carpenter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to build a houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ewes not his timber at aduenture; but before hand proiects in his mind the ſeueral rooms and parts; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly prepares his timber; and layes not ſparres in the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor groundſels, and ſtuds in the roofe; but fits euery one in his proper place, according to the modell and plot fore-conceiued in his mind: So my aduice is, that before thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; thou ſhouldeſt in thy minde, firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to thy ſelfe, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:465:24"/>generall place and heads of prayer with their order; which to bee contriued in the 1. which in the 2. which in the third place, with fore-caſting of ſome comely tranſitions, as doores to paſſe from one part to another. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, all the ſeuerall things which thou wouldeſt mention in thy prayer, to bee with diſcretion ranged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Generals, as for example: All things concerning faith, to bee referred to that Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is for faith: and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:465:24"/>which concerne repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to be marſhalled in that Petition which is for repentance, and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>The generall heades or places in ordinary priuate prayer would be theſe at the leaſt:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Confeſſion of ſinne.</item>
               <item>2 Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<list>
                     <item>1 For pardon.</item>
                     <item>2 For faith.</item>
                     <item>3 For repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</item>
                     <item>4 For directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall calling.</item>
                     <item>5 For perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</item>
                     <item>6 For the Church.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:465:25"/>
3 Thankeſ-giuing for bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, which are
<list>
                     <item>1. Spirituall, as Election, with the effects,
<list>
                           <item>1 Vocation</item>
                           <item>2 Iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                                 <desc>••••••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
                           <item>4 Hope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Temporall,
<list>
                           <item>1 Creation.</item>
                           <item>2 Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>dence in
<list>
                                 <item>1 Health.</item>
                                 <item>2 Liberty.</item>
                                 <item>3 Foode.</item>
                                 <item>4 Raiment.</item>
                                 <item>5 Friends.</item>
                                 <item>6 Manifold de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances &amp;c.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And ſo to conclude with petition for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the night o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day following, as is the occaſion.</p>
            <p>I binde no body to this order, but this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:465:25"/>take to be plaine for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners.</p>
            <p>I haue referred thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing to the laſt place, which may bee indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently vſed in the firſt: it matters not, ſo it bee not forgotten.</p>
            <p>Obſerue thine owne heart: if thou finde a cheerefulneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing for benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, then it's not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitting that thankeſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhould bee in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt place: If thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy heart more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with griefe for ſin, then if thou pleaſeſt, let confeſſion of ſin, and deſire of pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> precede
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:465:26"/>Wait vpon God wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an honeſt and reuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> heart, and the anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting will helpe thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> firmities, and teach th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to cry, <hi>Abba Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="example">
               <head>An example of the parts before propounded in their order.</head>
               <p>O Lord,</p>
               <p n="1">1 I confeſſe; that I am a vile ſinner.</p>
               <p n="2">2 I beſeech thee of.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Pardon by Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 O Lord, giue mee faith, that I may fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this pardon liuelily in my heart.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:465:26"/>
3 And I beſeech thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue mee true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance to amend my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icked life, that my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith may bee ſeene in the fruits of holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And whereas thou haſt called me to this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and calling (...) Direct mee therein I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umbly pray thee, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wiſedome of thy ſpirit, and furniſh mee with ſuch neceſſary gifts, that I may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my duty to thy glory, the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the comfort of mine owne ſoule.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And becauſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:465:27"/>is a deadly enemie, and I am weake; O Lord, I beſeech the forſake mee not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> houre of tentation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtabliſh my heart in grace, giue me perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in goodneſſe, and in the end victory by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6 This which I beg for my ſelfe, I humbly craue for thy whole Church vpon earth; that it may pleaſe thee to performe all thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to thine elect, and to bring vs all to thy heauenly kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> O Lord, thy name be for euer praiſed for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:465:27"/>all thy loue, and for all my benefits ſpirituall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd temporall, thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtowed vpon me. And I humbly intreat thee to preſerue me in ſafety this night, through my Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to whom, &amp;c. or, in whoſe name, &amp;c. praying in the words of the Lords prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>The ſame with the thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing in the firſt place.</head>
               <p>O Lord, I humbly thanke thee for all thy fauours ſpirituall and temporall, of the leaſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:465:28"/>of which I am moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie, by reaſon of my great ſinnes: for I confeſſe that I am a vile ſinner, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="enlargement">
               <head>The enlargement of theſe parts followeth.</head>
               <p>Before we particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k of enlargeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, be thou admoniſhed of 2. things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Feruent praying, though ſhort, is more accepted, then long praying with coldneſſe</p>
               <p>The Publicans prayer<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13.</note> was ſhort in words, but full of ſenſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; of more worth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:465:28"/>with God, then all the long praiers of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies: for God mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures not our deuotions by the length, and by the outward habite of words, but by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meaning of the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>So our bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the garden<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39.42.44.</note>, vſed but few words, but his deſire, and the gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of his ſpirit (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the power of our prayers) were vnuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Hee that vſeth many words, without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the heart, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth indeed, but prayeth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:465:29"/>not: for prayer is the deſire of the heart, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Abba Father;</hi> words but the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this deſire.</p>
               <p>The noyſe of our lips, without the voice of the heart, is no more a true prayer, then ringing of belles, or babling of a Parrot.</p>
               <p>As a body without a ſoule, much wood without fire; a bullet in a gun, without powder; ſo are words in prayer without ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Prayers are as gold; in a little quantitie of words, there muſt bee a great value of ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:465:29"/>
He that is feruent in the ſpirit, prayes much, though he ſpeake little.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, when thou prayeſt, let thy words follow thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
               <p>If thou findeſt a dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit, and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy affections; be the ſhorter; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with a groning of the ſpirit for thy drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, &amp; with a lifting vp thy heart to God, that hee would looke mercifully vpon thee, and quicken thee. Let this bee an occaſion to humble thee the more; and it will be a meanes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:465:30"/>to worke thee to more liuelineſſe and feruency the next time thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt thy ſelfe before God. And if thou bee'ſt truly humbled, it will driue thee to God, and thou wilt thinke long till the time come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, wherin thou maiſt complaine and poure forth thy heart before him.</p>
               <p>If thou findeſt a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacity and cheerfulnes of minde, and the deſire of thy heart to be ſtrong and feruent, prompting thee with matter and words; conclude not thy praiers and praiſes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:465:30"/>too ſoone, but let thy ſoule take her fill of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall delicacies in her familiar confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with God.</p>
               <p>If the deſire of the heart be weak and faint, it is not to bee wearied and oppreſſed with words.</p>
               <p>The enlargement of the ſeueral parts in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer is either
<list>
                     <item>1. Generall or</item>
                     <item>2. Particular.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The generall is that which in common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to al the parts, and it is twofold.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The vſing of ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:465:31"/>deſcription of God whom wee inuocate, from his Attributes, Promiſes, Effects, &amp;c. Such a beginning hath the Lords Prayer, <hi>Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9.</note>. Thus began our Sauiour in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.36</note> Abba Father, all things are poſſible vnto thee. Thus <hi>lehoſophat</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his prayer<note n="x" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.6.7.8.9.10.</note>. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24.25.26.</note>: looke the places which are to long to be tranſcribed.</p>
               <p>Such deſcription is to be vſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Prayers, for the helping of our faith and aſſurance in which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:465:31"/>we ought to pray, and may alſo be well vſed in any of the ſeuerall parts when wee would ſtir vp faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A begging of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. So <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 5.1.2.3 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.1.2.</note>. Both theſe are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently vſed by <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 19.15.16.</note>. This alſo may very fitly bee vſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of our prayers; as thus <hi>Daniel</hi> moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately and feruently endeth<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> 9.17.18.19.</note>.</p>
               <p>The particular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement is of each part by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The arguments ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſeruing hereunto, are the cauſes. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:465:32"/>The ſubiects. The adiuncts. The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Similitudes and compariſons. Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>There are certaine ornaments alſo not to be neglected, for the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and beautifying our ſpeech in prayer, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Comely tranſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and paſſings from one part to another.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Exclamations; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpeak of the goodnes of God, thus, How great is thy goodnes to them which feare thee<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19.</note>! When we ſpeake of the promiſes, thus; How
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:465:32"/>ſweete are thy promiſes to my mouth<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.103</note>! When wee ſpeake of our owne wretchedneſſe, thus; O wretched man that I am<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.24.</note>! &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Interrogations: as when <hi>Dauid</hi> lay vnder a great affliction of mind, and cried out: Will the Lord abſent himſelfe for euer? And will hee ſhew no more fauour? Is his mercy cleane gone for euer? Doth his promiſe faile for euermore? Hath God forgotten to bee mercifull? Hath he ſhut vp his tender mercies in diſpleaſure<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.7.8.9</note>?</p>
               <p>The power of theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:465:33"/>Interrogations? Who is able to expreſſe it? Whoſe heart ake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not in the very reading of them? How doe they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our feeling, and raiſe our deſires!</p>
               <p n="4">4 Options or wiſhes; as if we begge for grace to obey God according to his comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements, thus; O that my waies were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5.</note>.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Vowes and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thus;<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12.13.</note> Reſtore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me the ioy of thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and vphold mee with thy free Spirit. Then will I teach tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors thy waies, &amp;c.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:465:33"/>And againe;<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 14.</note> Deliuer mee, O God, and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſſe. And againe;<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15.</note> O Lord open thou my lippes, &amp; my mouth ſhal ſhew forth day praiſe. So alſo;<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.33.34.</note> Teach me, O Lord, the way of thy ſtatutes, and I will keepe it vnto the end: Giue mee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and I will keepe thy Law; yea, I will obſerue it with my whole heart.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Ingeminations; thus <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo prayeth,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.1.2.</note> O Lord God the Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, O God the Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſhew thy ſelfe; exalt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:465:34"/>thy ſelfe, O Iudge of the world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And diuers others of this nature, which a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout hart will eaſily find out: and to this purpoſe, I am perſwaded, its very helpeſfull to be familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſant in the Pſalmes, becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man of all other, of inflamed affection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and moſt excelling this way.</p>
               <p>Hee that deſires to make trial of this plaine direction, and to profit by it, may be much hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Let him indeuour ſoundly to vnderſtand
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:465:34"/>the principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or elſe he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to tell what to aske of God.</item>
                  <item>2 Secondly, if he can write, let him make a book of clean paper, and in ſundry leaues, write in the top the particular parts of prayer, with their ſeuerall branches, allowing a whole leafe to each part &amp; branch; and then whatſoeuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent &amp; ſpeciall phraſe or ſentence hee readeth or heareth of any of thoſe parts or branches, let him referre it to his proper leafe and place. Which courſe if it bee
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:465:35"/>taken, and theſe pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s diligently ſtudied, and now and then reuiſed &amp; read ouer, wil (in my opinion) much enable a man vpon any occaſion to pray with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, either alone, or with others to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired comfort.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If any ſhall think this way to be too buſie, and to require too much paines, I deſire them to remember, that no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing can be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without labour; which, how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſhould be, ſhould not be grutched, for the attaining a faculty in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:465:35"/>this exerciſe, which is the refuge, and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the ſoule: one of the chiefeſt pieces of a Chriſtians armour<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18.</note>, and the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all good things are ſanctified to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vſe<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</note>.</p>
               <p>Seuen yeere is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den but a conuenient terme, to learne the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men earthly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall trades; let not the childe of God account twice ſo long time to be too much, to learne the heauenly Art of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward crying Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="examples">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:465:36"/>
               <head>Here follow ſome examp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the rules of generall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> particular enlargement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deliuered, (for a taſte) to a young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner.</head>
               <p>The general enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from a deſcript<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of God,<note place="margin">Deſcription from</note> and begging of Audience, thus:</p>
               <p>O<note n="q" place="margin">Title.</note> Almighty God the<note n="r" place="margin">Effect.</note> Creatour of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and my moſt mercifull<note n="ſ" place="margin">Title.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ieſus Chriſt, which haſt gratiouſly<note n="t" place="margin">Promiſe.</note> promiſed to heare thy children when they pray vnto thee; O<note n="u" place="margin">Begging of Audience.</note> Lord I beſeech thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, heare, and grant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:465:36"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſupplication of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ruant by Ieſus Chriſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="examples">
               <head>Examples of particular enlargement.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Confeſſion of ſin may be enlarged, firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Adiunct;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i iunct.</note> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by a diſtribution of ſinne; thirdly, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, &amp;c. Thus,</p>
               <p>O Lord, I confeſſe that I am a vile ſinner.</p>
               <p>Firſt, being aſhamed to look vp vnto heauen, and vnworthy to liue vpon earth.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> for I am guilty of the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> and more alſo I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:465:37"/>haue committed actuall tranſgreſſions without number, in breaking thy moſt holy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, omitting my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and doing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; many ſinnes of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance (which I pleade not to excuſe, but to condemne my ſelf, who ought to haue knowne thy will), and often of knowledge, which wounds my ſoule to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Effect.</hi>
                  </note> O Lord in thy iuſtice I haue defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuch plagues both bodily and ſpirituall, temporall, and eternall, which thy righteous
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:465:37"/>omnipotency can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon abominable ſinners. Or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Petition for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don may be enlarged.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by an ingemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects adorned with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, by a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony adorned with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerrogation.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, by the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe. Thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
                  </note> O Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, O Lord forgiue, O Lord be mercifull.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Effects with excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> bleſſed is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:465:38"/>the man whoſe iniquity is forgiuen, and whoſe ſinne is couered. Bleſſed is the man that obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thy fauour.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Contraries.</hi>
                  </note> O Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, reward mee not according to my ill deſeruing. Turne away thine anger, and make thy ioyfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſhine into my ſoule.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Teſtimony with inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation.</note> is it not thy promiſe to pardon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that ſeeke thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour? and to helpe them which call vpon thee? O make good thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto thy ſeruant.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:465:38"/>Deare Father, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
               <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Meritorious cauſe.</note> remember his obedience, his paſſion, his blood, the price wherby I am ranſomed, and bee reconciled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all mine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Petition for faith may be enlarged.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from the contrary.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, adorned with vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. Thus,</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Efficient cauſe.</note> O Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee worke in me by thy holy Spirit faith
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:465:39"/>to beleeue the pardon of my ſinnes. It is not in my power to beleeue, it muſt be thy worke in my ſoule.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Contrary.</hi>
                  </note> make mee to belieue, good Father, and helpe my vnbeliefe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Effect with vowing.</note> grant mee a feeling of thy loue in my heart, and that peace which paſſeth all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then will I confidently come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and praiſe thee with ioyfull lips, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Petition for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may be enlarged.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the cauſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:465:39"/>adorned with exclamation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from the contrarie.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, from a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. Thus,</p>
               <p>Firſt, holy Father,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> The cauſe.</note> grant that my faith may ſhew it ſelfe in the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of my life.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Diſtribution with excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> and to this end I humbly beſeech thee renew in mee thy decaied image, and giue me true repentance, that I may turne from all my ſinnes, to ſerue thee in holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all the daies of my life. Make me to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand mine owne vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:465:40"/>that I may earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for renouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Ah wretch that I am! though I know my ſelfe to be an horrible ſinner; and that I haue tenne thouſand times deſerued damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet ſuch is the flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of my heart, that I am not ſenſible of my dangerous and fearefull eſtate.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Contrary.</hi>
                  </note> Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all things are poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thee; manifeſt, I pray thee thy gracious power vpon my heart, in mollifying the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it. Make me to relent and to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe. Worke in mee a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:465:40"/>godly ſorrow, and ſuch hatred of all ſinne, that I may for euer abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Compariſon.</hi>
                  </note> and grant deare Father, that I may be able as zealouſly to follow thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as euer I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully followed and fulfilled mine owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull deſires: or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Petition for dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in our perſonall calling may bee enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the cauſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from the contrarie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:465:41"/>
Fourthly, from the Adiunct, thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, O Lord in as much as thou haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that wee ſhould all liue in ſome honeſt calling, and that therein wee ſhould ſhew forth our faith and holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. I humbly intreat thee to direct me in this my vocation. (...)</p>
               <p>Secondly, Lord make me conſcionable, and to abhorre idleneſſe. Bleſſe my labours; grant that the world carrie not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my heart, but that I may ſo care for the things of this life, that I forget not that I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:465:41"/>to thy Kingdome. O make me ſo to liue as one, who through thy goodneſſe expects that heauenly inheritance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, let my life bee to thy glory, the good of others, and mine owne eternall comfort.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, and in as much as thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Croſſe to thy Diſciples; I beſeech thee to ſanctifie whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer trouble it ſhall pleaſe thee to lay vpon me, and to giue me pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſuch conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe with thy holy will, that it may not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:465:42"/>draw me from thee, but vnto thee, and that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame I may haue cauſe to reioyce in the experience of thy fauors through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord: or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Petition for perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may be enlarged.</p>
               <p n="1">1 From the cauſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 From the adiunct.</p>
               <p n="3">3 From the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, when ſpeciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may bee made of that ſpeciall corruption which we are moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto: thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1 O Lord let it bee thy good pleaſure,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
                  </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to watch ouer me, and to preſerue me
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:465:42"/>in the zealous perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of my duty to the end of my daies, which without thy helpe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For the daies are euill and dangerous,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Adiunct.</hi>
                  </note> the occaſions and examples of ſinne are infinite; Lord keepe mee in the faith, that I fall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and preſerue mee from the ſinnes of theſe times.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And more then this,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Contrary.</hi>
                  </note> Satan is my deadly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure my ſoule, and I am weake, O Lord thou knoweſt: Deare Father, confound Satan, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:465:43"/>confirme my faith: ſo bridle him, that he may not haue power ouer me: ſo ſtrengthen mee, that I may bee alwaies able to reſiſt and repell him: when thou ſhalt thinke it good to ſuffer him to tempt mee, O Lord forſake mee not: faile not of thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed helpe, that I may not faile in my faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: make mee to preuaile, and by the might of thy ſpirit, to haue victory in Ieſus Chriſt. And whereas I am compaſſed about with many infirmities, ſpecially with (...) O
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:465:43"/>Deare God and Father, ſtrengthen me here, and giue mee power to rule and gouerne my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to ſubdue them all to the obedience of thy holy word, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord. Or ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Petition for the Church may bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged,
<list>
                     <item>1 Generally.</item>
                     <item>2 Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Generally, by deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the fulfilling of all the promiſes made vnto it; as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Defence.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Deſtruction of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:465:44"/>
3 Conuerſion of the elect.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Confirmation of the conuerted.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Comfort of the afflicted, by
<list>
                     <item>Common ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of
<list>
                           <item>Body</item>
                           <item>Mind</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Speciall, as perſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In affliction of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That God would ſanctiſie it to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That hee would giue them patience.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer them, if it bee his will: if otherwiſe,</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:465:44"/>
4 That hee would prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able departure.</p>
               <p>In affliction of mind, that God would,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Pardon their ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Giue them repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Encreaſe their faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Defend them from Satan, and,</p>
               <p n="5">5 Giue them an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py iſſue.</p>
               <p>In Perſecution, that they may be</p>
               <p n="1">1 Aſſiſted with the holy ſpirit, and that they may</p>
               <p n="2">2 Boldly glorifie God, in witneſſing to the truth, euen with the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:465:45"/>loſſe of their liues.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Particularly, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mention of the Churches of England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Scotland, and Ireland that God would,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Pardon our cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hold backe his heauie iudgements de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Continue his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Preſerue our dread Soueraigne Lord, King <hi>Iames,</hi> our Noble <hi>Queen</hi> the hopefull Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Bleſſe the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Councell, Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Gentry, Iudges, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:465:45"/>the Miniſters of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty. And here we are to remember our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, parents, friends; yea our very enemies, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thankeſ-giuing may be enlarged by an enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of benefits, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; and may be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably amplified, by the contraries, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how miſerable wee ſhould be, in the want of thoſe bleſſings, all or ſome, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the concluſion we
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:465:46"/>may remember to aske preſeruation for the day or night following<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aptly falling into it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the mention of the benefits beſtowed vpon our bodies, in the thankeſ-giuing</p>
               <p n="1">1 For the day, taking occaſion by ſimilituder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to deſire grace to walke ſoberly as in the day.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For the night, by ſimilitude to deſire to be preſerued from the works of darkneſſe, and from eternall death, and that God would giue protection, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable refreſhing.</p>
               <p>Both for night and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:465:46"/>day to bee amplified from the ſhortneſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, and ſuddenneſſe of death; and to adde ſomething for prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereunto. For the life of a Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought to be a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll meditation of death. And thus reuerently to ſhut vp all with the Lords prayer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:465:47"/>
            <head>A SHORT PRAIER according to the ſame order, gathered out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; by which, as by a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, may bee conceiued, both the manner, and the vſe of a Note-booke, to be made and kept of thoſe things which we reade, concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of Prayer.</head>
            <p>O<note n="a" place="margin">The preface in a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God; and a begging of audience.</note> Lord my God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.14.</note>; I beſeech thee haue reſpect to the prayer of thy ſeruant, and to his ſupplication, to hearken to the cry, and to the prayer
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:465:47"/>which thy ſeruant prayeth before thee this day<note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 8.28.</note>. <note n="d" place="margin">Confeſſion of ſinne.</note> O my God, I am aſhamed, and bluſh to lift vp my face to thee my God: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine iniquities are encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer my head, and my treſpaſſe is growne vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.6.</note>. <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Petition, for pardon.</note> O Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.19.</note>, and cauſe thy face to ſhine vpon thy ſeruant, for the Lords ſake<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.17.</note>. Take away all mine iniquitie, and receiue me graciouſly; ſo will I render the calues of my lips<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.3.</note>. <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> For ſaith.</note> O ſtir me vp to take hold vpon thee<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 64.7.</note>. I beleeue Lord, helpe my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.24</note>, and encreaſe my faith<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.5.</note> Seale me to the day of Redemption<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30.</note>, and ſhed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:465:48"/>abroad thy loue in my heart, by thy holy ſpirit<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.</note>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I humbly beſeech thee.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note> Turne me O Lord vnto thee, and I ſhall bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.21.</note>. Create in me a clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> heart O Lord, and rene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> right ſpirit within me<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10.</note>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take the ſtony heart out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my body, and giue me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart of fleſh, that I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> walke in thy flatutes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that I may be thy ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and thou mayſt be my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for euermore<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11.19.20.</note>. <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> For dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in our perſonall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</note> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whereas thou haſt ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> mee to this eſtate (... <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Good Lord grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grace, therin to worketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which is good<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.28. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12.</note>, with q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>etneſſe, and to eate mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>owne
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:465:48"/>bread, ſhewing all good conſcience, that I may adorne the doctrine of God my Sauiour in all things<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15.</note>. and in as much as thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples muſt take vp the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roſſe and follow thee<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24.</note>. I way thee, Deare Father, ſtrengthen mee with all might, through thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, vnto all pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce and long ſuffering, with ioyfulneſſe<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.11.</note>. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> For perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance.</note> And becauſe Satan as a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion, ſeeketh to deuour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, O my God, tread down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atan vnder my feet<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</note>; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh me in euery good word and work<note n="d" place="margin">2. <hi>Theſe.</hi> 17</note>, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue my whole ſpirit; ſoule and body, blameleſſe, vnto
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:465:49"/>the comming of our, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ieſus Chriſt.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> For the Church.</note> Doe good thy good pleaſure to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on, and build the mall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thy Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.18</note>. Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thy little flock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whom th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n haſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the kingdome<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32.</note>. <note n="h" place="margin">Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</note> I th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thee O Father, Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heauen and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25.</note>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou haſt, deliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the power of dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and tranſlated we into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kingdome of thine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue. O Lord, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been my God from my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbe<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 22.10.</note> Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pt mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto this, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thy pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dence, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> giuen me bread to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> clothes to put on<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 28.20.</note>. I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:465:49"/>praiſe thy name, and I beſeech thee, make me dwel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſafety<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</note>, vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of thy wings<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.8.</note>, this day (or night) through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Chriſt; in whoſe name, &amp;c. Or, to whom with thee O Father. Amen.</p>
            <div type="example">
               <head>Thou maiſt alſo make vſe of the Lords Prayer, excellently to this purpoſe.</head>
               <p>IT was giuen for a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, and ſpeciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to the Church vpon earth, how to pray.</p>
               <p>There can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:465:50"/>direction: for if wee require wiſdome; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe endited it: if perfection; it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all the kinds of all things to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for: if order; the method is diuine: if perſpicuous breuity; ſo much could not by any onely-created vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be compacted into ſo little: if force and power, there can bee none more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then that, which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Word of the Father, hath left and commended to his Church.</p>
               <p>If thou wouldeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:465:50"/>vſe it, Obſerue beſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Learne through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnderſtand it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Beare in mind the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerall petitions, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e it order.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Note downe in thy memory, as thou wert before directed, theſe graces thou craueſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uery petition, giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their proper place, in thy booke, in thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and in thy prayer.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, take due knowledge of thy wants in euery petition; vnder their ſeuerall heads ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the phraſes and things thou mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:465:51"/>with al concerning them. And ſpecially note vpon thy heart, and imprint in it the graces thou moſt want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, &amp; the wants which moſt doe trouble thee Principally, meditate of thoſe graces, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bee humbled with the feeling of thoſe wants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>To helpe thee to ſpell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this leſſon out of the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>After a deſcription of God, as before, keeping the petitions with their order, in thy minde,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:465:51"/>thou maiſt enlarge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us.</p>
               <div n="1" type="petition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 1. Petition:</hi> Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Heere thou maiſt how how God hath commanded, and it is our dutie to glorifie his name, in regard of our</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Creation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but ſpecially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Redemption.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Then acknowledge,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, thy negligence and careleſneſſe this way.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, thy pride,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:465:52"/>in ſeeking thine owne glory more then Gods.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, thy want of zeale.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, ſuch ſinnes whereby thou haſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured God moſt, cauſing his name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be blaſphemed.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Deſire grace, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou maieſt, chiefly in all thy thoughts, words, and deeds, propound to thy ſelf to glorifie God, and to reſpect his glory more then euen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of thy ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="petition">
                  <head>The 2. Petition: <hi>Thy Kingdome come.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1 Enlarge this, by a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:465:52"/>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy ſoule vnto God, for thy bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnder ſinne and Satan, amplified from the conſideration</p>
                  <p>Firſt, of our firſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent traiterous, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious diſpoſition, by the power of originall ſinne, which hath whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſed all parts of body and ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Deſire that God would</p>
                  <p>Firſt, reſcue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme thee out of the power of Satan, and ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that hee
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:465:53"/>would by his ſpirit rule in thy heart, caſting out the ſtrong man, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding his ſpoyles.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that hee would make the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſubiect to the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſpirit, and renew thee according to his image.</p>
                  <p>Thou maiſt make this the place of repentance.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Here thou maiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Church, the kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="petition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 3. Petition:</hi> Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heauen.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Here confeſſe and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:465:53"/>bewaile,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, thy readineſſe to doe thine owne will, yea the will of Satan, making theſe the rule of thy life, and not the will of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, thy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods word, which is the copie of his will.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, thy negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in hearing of it.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſhewed in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in knowne ſins, after admonition.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Then deſire grace.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to denie thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:465:54"/>the word.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to loue and reuerence it more.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to make it the rule of thy life, in as much as it is the ſcepter of Chriſts kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, that thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation may bee in heauen, after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Angels.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, whatſoeuer be the will of God for thee to doe or ſuffer, that thou maiſt alwaies with patience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation ſay: <hi>Thy will be done.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="petition">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:465:54"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 4. Petition:</hi> Giue vs this day our daily bread.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Here acknowledge that thy life, preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all good things come from God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Confeſſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile thy</p>
                  <p>Firſt, couetouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, thy vniuſt dealing, to enrich and maintaine thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> thy diſtruſt in the good prouidence of God, who feedeth the fowles, clotheth the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, thy earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:465:55"/>and worldly mind that cannot ſauor ought but earth and earthly things.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Then deſire,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the prouidence of God to watch ouer thee for thy preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and main tenance.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, faith to reſt vpon God in all eſtates &amp; not vpon the meanes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, not to vſe vnlawfull meanes.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that God would bleſſe his gifts vnto thee, and that thou mayſt vſe them ſoberly and comfortably.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, thou mayſt here make vſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:465:55"/>concerning thy perſonall calling.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="petition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>5 Petition;</hi> Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Here make vſe of the confeſſion of ſin, and petition for pardon, for faith and repentance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former direction.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Here alſo deſire a charitable heart toward thy neighbours, as thou deſireſt to bee forgiuen, ſo to forgiue others, and to be ready to grant the pardon thou craueſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="petition">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:465:56"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>6. Petition;</hi> Leade vs non into tentation: but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euill.</head>
                  <p>Here deſire ſtrength againſt Satan his tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and againſt all things, whereby thou mayſt be drawne from faith in God and holy obedience, making vſe of that which is in the Petition for perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance according to the former direction.</p>
                  <p>And for concluſion, as our Sauior concludes with a kind of praiſe to God, ſo doe thou.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:465:56"/>
The heads of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes thou mayſt make the graces which God hath giuen thee, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to euery petition.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for making thee in any meaſure ſtudious of his glory.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for giuing thee his Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for his word.</p>
                  <p>Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee;
<list>
                        <item>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</item>
                        <item>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</item>
                     </list> thee</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, for pardon of ſinne: Iuſtification, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, for ſtrength in any tentation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:465:57"/>
If thou wilt beſtow ſome time and ſtudy to practiſe according to this, I cannot but be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that thou ſhalt find much benefit, which God grant.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, I would admoniſh a learner, of fiue things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, enter not vpon the practiſe here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, till thou haſt theſe generall proiects perfect in thy head, or ſome other.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in the meane time make vſe of ſome good praier-book, and out of it get by hart ſuch prayers as beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:465:57"/>thy deuotion and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; or if thou canſt not reade, vſe ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers help to reade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or repeate them to thee; at leaſt neglect not to ſay vpon thy knees reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently the Lords prayer: alwaies prouided, that thou well vnderſtand the meaning of euery petition, or otherwiſe thou ſhalt take GODS name in vaine.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, giue not ouer this courſe, though thou findeſt it hard, but ouercome the difficulty with thy diligence and paines. To giue ouer a good exerciſe for diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:465:58"/>argues idleneſſe and ſloth.</p>
                  <p>All good things are hard to vs, becauſe of our corruption, and prayer of all holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes the hardeſt: wee muſt force nature.</p>
                  <p>Children learne not to ſpeake perfectly in a day, or a moneth; much leſſe can wee crie Abba Father perfectly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly vpon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
                  <p>Redeeme ſome of the time thou beſtoweſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy pleaſures and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and beſtow it this way; it ſhal neuer repent thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:465:58"/>
Fourthly, remember that the Phariſies could make excellent prayers, and the Reprobate can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ie Lord, Lord.</p>
                  <p>A wicked man may attaine thus farre, as to make prayers very nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but with feeling and in faith to cry Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a wicked man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. This is prayer, and a certaine token of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, the other is not.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, labor to haue grace in thy heart; and whatſoeuer thou askeſt in prayer, practiſe in life.</p>
                  <p>He that prayes for the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:465:59"/>pardon of his ſinnes, and for grace to liue well, and yet neither en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth to auoid ſin, or to practiſe pietie, mockes God, and ſhall not goe vnpuniſhed.</p>
                  <p>Liue as thou prayeſt, that thou mayeſt liue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                  <p>So be it.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 66.18.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>If I regard wickedneſſe in my heart, the Lord will not beare me.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2. TIM. 2.19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let euery one that calleth on the name of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquitie.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:465:59"/>
Now to the only wiſe God, who is able to doe aboue all wee aske or thinke, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, bee praiſe in the Church throughout all generations for euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="admonitions">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:465:60"/>
            <head>Short and godly Admonitions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Time, and the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ered out of Eph. 5.16.</head>
            <div type="admonition">
               <head>Redeeming the Time; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the daies are euill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <p>Here are two par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <list>
                     <item>An exhortation, <hi>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> the Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A reaſon: <hi>Becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> dayes are euill.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="admonition">
               <head>Redeeming the time.</head>
               <p>TIme is the meaſure of Motion.</p>
               <p>Opportunity is that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:465:60"/>part of time which is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for our affaires.</p>
               <p>This is meant here, as it is the meaſure of good motions, called alſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſeaſon, due time.</p>
               <p>It is the beautie of things; for euery thing is beautifull in his time<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.11</note>.</p>
               <p>Meates are welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, when they are in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; ſo a word ſpoken in due ſeaſon is comely<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 25.11</note>; Euen a refreſhing of the wearie ſoule<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 51.4.</note>.</p>
               <p>As ſome impriſon truth in vnrighteouſnes<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.</note>, ſo doe, they time<note n="(e)" place="margin">Hierome.</note>.</p>
               <p>It is charitie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme time, by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:465:61"/>
Opportunitie of time is a rich commoditie; the couetouſneſſe of it to doe well, is an honeſt couetouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>As Merchants<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue carefully the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of buying in, and venting their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, ſo buy thou and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme time to doe good.</p>
               <p>They that looſe time, are the greateſt looſers, and waſtfulleſt prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals; for of all other poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, two may be had together: but two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of time cannot be poſſeſſed together.</p>
               <p>This precious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:465:61"/>is moſt out of requeſt with great and rich men; who conſume and miſpend time, as faſt as their vnthriftie children doe their inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritances.</p>
               <p>Idleneſſe, vanity, and neglecting the pretious time, is the diſeaſe of great and rich men, as they ſay the Gout is: theſe can find time, to dally, to court, to be rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, &amp;c. but not to pray and ſerue God; therfore for the moſt part, they are moſt poore in the beſt things.</p>
               <p>Time is the price of time; when thy profit,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:465:62"/>thy pleaſure, thy vaine delights, thy luſts, call thee after them: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change time for time.</p>
               <p>As thou giueſt thy money for meate, and apparrell; ſo giue theſe things to purchaſe the time of prayer, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, Buy the truth<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.23</note>: but <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaith; What is truth<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 18.38</note>? ſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, buy the time: but our profane wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſay, What is time? let vs ſpend it, ſay they, as though it were little worth.</p>
               <p>Time is Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he allowes thee no
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:465:62"/>time to bee vaine and wicked: but hee giues thee time, that thou mayſt repent and doe good. Make thy aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of it.</p>
               <p>Of the time thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweſt, in prayer, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Pſalmes, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scriptures, and good bookes, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, it ſhall neuer repent thee. But time otherwiſe ſpent, wil one day torment thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>Thou muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for time; on this moment depends eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; of bleſſedneſſe if it be well; of miſerie, if it
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:465:63"/>be ill imployed.</p>
               <p>It is great wiſdome to know the time, and to redeeme it<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.16</note>.</p>
               <p>The men of <hi>Iſachar</hi> were in great account with <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe they had vnderſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do; ſo are they in great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with God,<note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 12.32</note> who regard and vſe the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of well doing.</p>
               <p>When a poore man begs of thee, then haſt thou occaſion to ſhew thy charitie: when thou art in tentation, to ſhew thy faith: when thou art iniuried, to ſhew thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:465:63"/>when thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or ſeeſt men offend, to ſhew thy zeale: when there are publike mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings for the worſhip of God, to ſhew thy deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Looſe not ſuch faire opportunities of weldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to glorifie God.</p>
               <p>The time of grace and of the Goſpell is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the day of ſaluation. While the dore is open, enter into the Kingdom of heauen.</p>
               <p>While thou haſt the light, beleeue in the light; and walke in the light, that thou mayſt be the child of light.<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.35.36</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:465:64"/>
To day if thou wilt heare his voyce, harden not thy heart<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> while it is called to day<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13.</note>?</p>
               <p>The time is ſhort<note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.</note>: the art of weldoing is long: the worke is great: the labourers are lazie: the Maſter is at hand: It remaineth that wee vſe the world as though we vſed it not, and that wee redeeme the time of prayer, and of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>Occaſions are head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; and once paſt, not to bee recouered. The tide taries for none: take time while it is offered:
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:465:64"/>while you haue oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, doe good vnto all; to thy ſelf, to others, ſpecially to them which are of the houſehold of faith<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note>.</p>
               <p>The 5 fooliſh virgins came to late, and were ſhut out<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10.11.12.</note>. Ieruſalem in her day tooke no knowledge of the things belonging to her peace, and was deſtroyed<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42.</note>. <hi>Eſau</hi> came not in time, and loſt the bleſſing, but found leiſure enough to crie bitterly<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ</hi> 37.33.34.</note>.</p>
               <p>Our life is as a Fayre:<note n="t" place="margin">Nazian.</note> when the Fayre-day is ouer, there is no buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things thou nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:465:65"/>ſo when this life is ended, there is no time of repentance. Repent now; for in death no man remembreth God, ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.5.</note>.</p>
               <p>As in warre, ſo in deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, we are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to erre twice: of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doe well, that thou maiſt once die well, and thou ſhalt be happy.</p>
               <p>Liue euery day, as if it were thy laſt; and as at the laſt day thou wilt wiſh thou hadſt, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, thou haſt liued.</p>
               <p>Examine thine houres euery day: how many doeſt thou ſpend in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking? how
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:465:65"/>many in ſleeping? how many in dreſſing and trimming thy painted ſheath? how many in doing nothing? how many in doing that which is ill? how few or none in prayer and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing?</p>
               <p>How ill tenants are we to our grand Lord? wee hold all of him, but we thinke little of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and paying at our due time.</p>
               <p>Wee receiue all our time from God, and like vnthankefull wretches, ſerue him with the leaſt part of it, and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the laſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:465:66"/>
A Heathen Emperot<note n="x" place="margin">Titus, the ſonne of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian. Hierom on the ſixth to the Galathians.</note> accounted that day loſt, in which hee did no good. How many daies haſt thou loſt? Account thou likewiſe that a loſt day, in which thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeſt not better then thy ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Hee that moſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the time, liues long, though hee fulfill not much time; and he which is an hundred yeeres old, if he haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed no time of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, hath been (but hath not liued) long<note n="y" place="margin">Seneca.</note>.</p>
               <p>The Vſurer ſels time to men, and the diuell ſteales time from men.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:465:66"/>He tells the Papiſts of Purgatory: that painted fire, yeelds but a cold comfort: for by this meanes he leades them to hell in a ſtring: Hee telles our gallants, that its time enough to pray and repent when they are old: And by this meanes, they ſpend ſo much time in euill, that they leaue none for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, prayer, and for vſing meanes to ſaue their ſoules.</p>
               <p>As doth the Vſurer, ſo doth the diuel; the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer giues the young No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice faire words, till hee hath broken his day,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:465:67"/>and forfeited his lands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo doth the diuel-ſtroke vs, till by continuance in ſinne we are hardned and paſt recouery.</p>
               <p>Pray to day, repent to day: thou art not ſure of to morrow; he that is not ready and fit to day, will be leſſe to morrow.</p>
               <p>Thy life is like a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of weak wine, which is quicke and liuely at the firſt broching: but flat and ill taſted when it is tilted.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou draw out the firſt, and beſt of thy life to the diuell, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing drunkenneſſe, whoredome, and thy
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:465:67"/>lawleſſe luſts? &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue the dregs to God, which are fit to be poured out to the hogs?</p>
               <p>Is it a time then, firſt to begin to liue, when thou art ready to die? then firſt to ſeeke God, when thou commeſt to thy brothes, and ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? when vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, memorie, ſight, hearing, &amp; ſenſes faile.</p>
               <p>For the moſt part, they which defer the ſeaſon of ſeeking God till age; are then iuſtly giuen ouer to him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſerued in their youth, which is the diuell.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:465:68"/>
Remember thy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator in the dayes of thy youth; while the euill dayes come not, nor the yeeres draw nigh, when thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſi.</hi> 12.1.</note>. Thus did <hi>Samuel</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.28</note>; &amp; <hi>Timothy</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note>: God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in ſuch.</p>
               <p>Art thou old, and haſt trifled out thy Time, neglecting the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of knowing and ſeruing God? Diſpaire not, but repent; and be the more carefull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the Time that remaines.</p>
               <p>Let it ſuffice, that in the Time paſt of thy life
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:465:68"/>thou haſt walked as a Heathen, in abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wickedneſſe: But now the end of al things is at hand; be ſober ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and watch vnto prayer<note n="d" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Doe here, as thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in thy iourney. If thou haſt ouer-ſlept thy ſelfe in the morning; thou makeſt the ſhorter bait, and ſpurreſt the harder on: ſo now, put thy beſt legge before, make ſpeed, leſt thou be benighted, and ſhut out with the dogs and Sorcerers, and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel</hi> 27.15</note>, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:465:69"/>
                  <hi>Becauſe the dayes are euil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Time, is called Daies, becauſe it is counted by Dayes.</p>
               <p>Dayes are not euill in themſelues, and as they are a neceſſary apperte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to the frame of this world,<note n="f" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> which is Gods building: but they are ſo called, from euill perſons, and things<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34.</note> which are in thoſe dayes.</p>
               <p>The time is euill, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we which liue in ſuch Time are euill; &amp; when by our euill of ſin, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of puniſhment is
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:465:69"/>deſeruedly inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. Which puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments no maruell if they continue, when that continues in vs, which deſerues to bee puniſhed.</p>
               <p>The dayes are euill: then great need to vſe Prayer: for it ſhall come to paſſe, that whoſoeuer calles vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſafe<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Many men cry out, that the world was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer worſe, ſaying, O the Times! But are not the Times the worſe for thee? If thou beeſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and prophane; it is
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:465:70"/>thou which makeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo bad. Complaine not of the Times, but of thy ſelfe, and amende the Times by thy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Achan</hi> made it an euill day to the Iſraelites, by his ſinne<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 7.</note>; and <hi>Moſes</hi> made it a good day by his prayers<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 17 11</note>
               </p>
               <p>Wouldeſt thou ſee many dayes, and good? keepe thy tongue from euill, and thy lips from ſpeaking guile: depart from euil, and do good, ſeek peace &amp; enſue it<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 34.12.13.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As a noble Roman<note n="m" place="margin">Lucullus.</note> turned a diſmall day, into a ſucceſſefull, by
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:465:70"/>his valour: ſo turne thou euill dayes into good, by thy goodnes.</p>
               <p>The worſe the Dayes and Times be, the more precious let bee euery opportunity of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
               <p>As in times of derth, the poore man picks vp euery kernell of corne that falles beſide: O (ſaith hee) It's deare, none muſt beloſt: ſo loſe thou not one crum of Time, wherein thou maieſt haue occaſion to doe good: For the daies are euill.</p>
               <p>A man that ſhould in the time of famine giue
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:465:71"/>his corne to the hogs, were worthy to bee hanged vp at his gate; ſo art thou worthy to looſe the reward of wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, which throweſt away the opportunities thereof.</p>
               <p>There are millions in hell, who if they had it, would giue all the wealth in the world, for one dayes opportunity of repentance, which they deſpiſed and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlowed, when they liued vpon the earth.</p>
               <p>As the Bee, ſo ſoone as euer the Sun breakes forth, flies abroad to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honey and wax; ſo
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:465:71"/>be thou ready to euery good worke<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.</note>, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the occaſion therof.</p>
               <p>Many ſay, that they haue no Time to learne to pray, to heare the word, &amp;c. The voice of a beaſt. Haſt thou a time to eate, to ſleepe, to liue? Haſt thou Time to dance after the diuels pipe? and can'ſt finde no Time to learne god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe?</p>
               <p>Many ſay they would haue prayed, heard, &amp;c. but that they had impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments? Redeem now the time, and ſtep ouer impediments.</p>
               <p>Hee that obſerueth
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:465:72"/>the wind ſhal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and hee that is afraid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> euery cloud, ſhall n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reape<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſi.</hi> 11.4</note>: ſo hee that will not doe good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of impediment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall neuer doe good for ſo long as there is a diuell, and a world, and an vnregenerate part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> there will bee impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, euen a thouſand when thou wouldeſt do good, and a thouſand furtherances when thou wouldeſt doe euill.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Paul</hi> had cenſed to preach at Epheſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, of impediments, when ſuch a dore was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnto him<note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.9.</note>, he
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:465:72"/>had loſt the comfort of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ring there ſo famous Church.</p>
               <p>The more are the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſaries and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, be thou the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atchfull vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons of doing good.</p>
               <p>The dayes are euill, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> men are euill that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue in theſe dayes. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our thou to be good; and ſo to liue, as thou wouldeſt wiſh to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound liuing, when Chriſt ſhall come to iudgement.</p>
               <p>Pray, pray, pray; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent, repent: Bleſſed is that ſeruant, when his Lord when he
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:465:73"/>commeth ſhall find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doing<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.46.</note>. <hi>Amen, Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.11.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now it is high time awake out of ſleepe.</p>
                  <p>The night is far ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> the day is at hand; let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> therefore caſt off the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of darkneſſe, and put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the armour of light.</p>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:465:73"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
